[Music]
hello and welcome everyone
it's april 28 2022 and we're here in
actin flab live stream number 43.0
discussing predictive coding a
theoretical experimental review
welcome to the actin actinflab we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning
practicing applied active inference you
can find us at links here on the slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome
and we'll be following video etiquette
for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org if you want to learn
more about how to participate in the
live streams or anything else happening
in actin flap
okay
we're here today to learn and discuss
the paper predictive coding a
theoretical and experimental review by
baron millage anil seth and christopher
buckley
the video is just an introduction in a
contextualization for some of the ideas
and some of the details of the paper in
the broad sense
it's not a review or a final word
it's uh as with some of these other
technical dense papers it's like an
opening for those who have technical
questions at the learning side of things
or at the more
advanced research side of things to come
get involved because this is a technical
paper but also hopefully as will unpack
it has a lot of cool biological and
philosophical implications
in 43.0 we're going to say hello and
introduce some big questions then cover
the aims and claims of the paper the
abstract and the roadmap and then pretty
much just jump right in
and we're going to focus a lot on the
introduction the context and the single
layer predictive coding model and then
we'll go a little bit faster through the
later sections of the paper talking
about some generalizations of predictive
coding and some important points that
the authors race so if you want to
participate in 43.1 or 0.2 in the coming
weeks just let us know
okay so we can say hello
and give any information that we'd like
and also just maybe something that we
thought was exciting or something that
motivated us to get involved in this
quite involved paper
so i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and i was curious to learn more about
how predictive coding and predictive
processing related to active inference
and also just about how different models
framed anticipatory systems
so over to you maria
hello daniel and everyone
um i have a bi-color degree in
psychology and i am a master's candidate
in philosophy of science
in the university of sao paulo brazil
and i
am researching the relationship between
predictive processing and illusionist
theories of consciousness
and i think what brought me here today
was
uh
my my wish to start learning about the
formalisms because i don't really see it
in philosophy and i don't actually need
it for my dissertation but eventually i
wanted to continue my my work on
predictive processing so eventually i
had to start it and i just thought about
maybe that's a good idea
to come here and minimize my
uncertainties
awesome through inference and or through
action and also thanks a lot brock for
helping in the dot zero
so we'll just start with the big
questions and these are the kind of
questions that might motivate someone or
interest them in this paper without even
mentioning active inference per se but
these are like some big questions that
get touched upon
what is the formal basis of predictive
coding
how is predictive coding used or useful
what are some areas of current and
future development and what is the
relationship between predictive coding
and active inference and hopefully we'll
draw out more questions
anything else to add about this
no not really
cool
the paper is predictive coding a
theoretical an experimental review i
think the first version was from 2021
but the second revised version was 22
by millage seth and buckley and just to
review
the
core claim and then some of the aims and
directions they set out
they write that no comprehensive review
of predictive coding theory and
especially of recent developments in the
field exists that's their claim
and then they aim towards
providing a comprehensive review both of
the core mathematical structure and
logic of predictive coding so there's a
mathematical review
and summarization aspect to the paper
and then they also review a wide range
of classic and recent work within the
framework ranging from biologically
realistic micro circuits that could
implement predictive coding to the close
relationship between predictive coding
and the widely used back propagation of
error algorithm
as well as surveying the close
relationship between predictive coding
and modern machine learning techniques
that's how they set out where they want
to go
um would you like to read the first
slide of the abstract
okay
um so
predictive coding offers a potentially
unifying account of cortical function
postulating that the core function of
the brain is to minimize prediction
errors with respect to a generative
model of the world
the theory is closely related to the
bayesian brain framework and over the
last two decades has gained substantial
influence in the fields of theoretical
and cognitive neuroscience
a large body of research has arisen
based on both empirically testing
improved and extended theoretical and
mathematical models of predictive coding
as well as in evaluating their potential
biological possibility for
implementation in the brain and concrete
neurophysiological and psychological
predictions made by the theory
despite this enduring popularity however
no comprehensive review of predictive
coding theory and especially of recent
development developments in these fields
exists
they write
here we provide a comprehensive review
of
both of the core mathematical structure
and logic of predictive coding thus
complementing recent tutorials in the
literature
and
we also review a wide range of classic
and recent work within the framework
which is what we had read previously in
the ames so that's how the authors
describe their own work and now we're
going to
see their road map see how they went
about getting there and then we're gonna
jump right into the introduction and
then the formalisms
so here we see the roadmap
and the the rough outline of the paper
is as follows
section one provides an introduction
that contextualizes predictive coding
and we'll also be unpacking it in a
philosophical and historical view
section two
provides
an initial pass on the one level
predictive coding model sort of the
kernel or the archetype or the motif of
predictive coding and connects it
importantly to variational inference
then predictive coding is generalized or
extended or elaborated in a few
important directions so like in section
2.2
it's generalized into a multi-level case
in section 2.3 the concept of
generalized coordinates are introduced
in section 4
precision is introduced as a concept and
in section 2.5 it's connected back to
the brain
section 3 discusses paradigms of
predictive coding
both unsupervised and supervised
and also connects it through those
sections and others to some research in
machine learning
and then in section 4 there's
connections between predictive coding
and some other algorithms
both those algorithms that are common in
machine learning and computational
statistics like the error back
propagation
linear predictive coding and column
filtering and normalizing flows and
biased competition
and then in section 4.5
explicit connection is drawn between
predictive coding and active inference
which brings in the cost of action as
well as the idea of pid control and the
discussion section closes with just a
few other thoughts and summaries and
directions and challenges
and there's several appendices so
it's a long ish paper or monograph but
it's an excellent paper and we're just
going to cover
more of an emphasis on the context and
the beginning and then sort of skip over
or trail off over a few things but
there's lots of unpacks so i hope that
we can like learn more in the coming
weeks if the authors want to join or if
anybody else wants to join
anything to add on roadmap or ready for
introduction
let's go all right awesome
so
um i'll just add uh some notes from this
section of the introduction and then
maria feel free to add anything
so how do they introduce predictive
coding they introduce predictive coding
theory as an influential theory in
computational and cognitive
neurosciences which proposes a potential
unifying theory of cortical function
that's like related to the cortex of the
brain
namely that the core function of the
is to minimize prediction error
where the prediction error signals
mismatches between predictive input and
the input actually received minimizing
the divergence between expectations and
observations is going to be a big theme
and
approaching that minimization
it can be achieved in multiple ways and
they're colored differently here
through immediate inference about the
hidden states of the world
like i thought the ball is over here i'm
getting evidence it's over here so i
should just update how i think about the
world
which can explain perception like the
perception of a ball moving across the
visual field
through updating a global world model to
make better predictions which could
explain learning
like learning a little bit higher level
than just where the ball is in the
visual field but like where balls tend
to be in the visual field or how fast
they tend to move around
and finally through action to sample
sensory data from the world that
conforms to the predictions and that's
when we'll introduce action into
predictive coding in the latter sections
of the paper and then just last point
they say that predictive coding boasts
an extremely developed and principled
mathematical framework in terms of
variational inference as well as many
empirically tested computational models
that have close links to machine
learning
so that's how they introduce this is as
a unifying theory that integrates
inference as well as action inference of
different kinds more like perceptual and
more like learning
and they're saying that it has a very
rich mathematical framework and it's
been connected to insights in biology
and in machine learning
to add
nope
so they write predictive coding as a
theory also offers a single mechanism
that accounts for diverse perceptual and
neurobiological phenomena such as end
stopping by stable perception like
illusions
repeat repetition suppression illusory
motions and attentional modulation of
neural activity so they're pointing to
the integrative nature of this theory or
framework to model all of these diverse
phenomena as being an advantage like we
could have a special theory for just by
stable perception a special theory for
just repetition suppression and so on
but this is a framework by which those
outcomes are occurring as kind of
outcomes of an underlying
framework predictive coding rather than
needing special theories so that kind of
like parsimony or conciliance is pursued
in the areas like cognitive neuroscience
and they write as such and perhaps
uniquely among neuroscientific theories
predictive coding encompasses all three
layers of mars hierarchy
by providing well characterized and
importantly an empirically supported
view of what the brain is doing
at all of the computational algorithmic
and implementational levels
so
mars very influential hierarchy it's
kind of like tin bergens questions or a
little bit like maslow's hierarchy you
can think of it as like an organizing or
a sense-making framework again
to the question what are brains doing
and so we're going to have like three
different kinds of answers to what
brains are doing there's going to be an
answer at the level of computation
algorithm and implementation
and so
here with the example of a bird flying
the computational level is like flight
it's like the why what is the algorithm
doing it's a sorting algorithm what is
the brain doing in this situation it's
tracking a moving object
then there's the flapping level which is
the algorithm which is kind of like
pseudo code and that's suggesting
the what of how that y is realized like
what is happening in this sorting
algorithm well it's doing this this this
this this what is the flight function
being realized by it's being realized by
flapping of the wings
and then there's the implementation so
it's not just the flapping of anything
it's the flapping of something specific
and so that's the implementational
details
and those levels of analysis have been
helpful and provocative in connecting
computational cognitive theories to
neurobiological theories so it's been a
very influential
and
um
discussion
provoking framework that has helped
people connect as well as challenge some
of the similarities and differences
between like computers and braids
great
this is still in the introduction and
they're going to kind of give us a
qualitative perspective on predictive
coding and then we're going to be diving
into a lot more historical and technical
detail but how does predictive coding
work
the core intuition behind predictive
coding is that the brain is composed of
a hierarchy of layers which are each
making predictions about the activity of
the layer immediately below them in the
hierarchy so there's two directions in
this predictive coding multi-layer
scheme which we're just introducing here
as kind of a heuristic and then we're
going to zoom in to just what's
happening at one level and then we're
going to pull back out to kind of
recovering this multi-level formalism
the downward descending predictions at
each level that's the blue arrow
are compared with the activity and
inputs of each level level to form
prediction errors this is the
information in each layer which could
not be successfully predicted
these prediction errors are then fed
upwards that's the red arrow to serve as
inputs to higher levels which can then
be utilized to reduce their own
prediction error
so that's kind of the bigger picture
like the idea at the top level is like
i'm tracking
a soccer ball that's moving from the
left to the right
and then that gets transduced in certain
ways and that is
in this case resulting in kind of a
visual perceptive level prediction about
what one should expect to see
and this is again just the multi-level
predictive coding scheme that is often
used
but
we're gonna zoom back to just what's
happening at a single level and then
what is happening at multiple levels
awesome
here's a fun 2020 paper by er sorry 2018
paper by carl fristen does predictive
coding have a future
and this is going to provide just a
little bit of context and then we're
going to jump more into though
carl wrote in the 20th century we
thought the brain extracted knowledge
from sensation that's like the
recognition model and that's sort of the
incoming sensory processing model
the 21st century witnessed a strange
inversion in which the brain became an
organ of inference actively constructing
explanations for what's going on out
there beyond its sensory epithelia one
paper played a key role in this paradigm
shift
and carl goes on to write that a 1999
paper by rao and ballard which we're
going to talk more about for him was one
of those papers that's a once in a
decade find
so
we're going to talk more about it but
this is just kind of connecting it early
to
carl firsten's line of research the
connection between active inference and
predictive coding and the idea that
sometimes it's these early
transdisciplinary papers that can stitch
two different fields together and that
that can have long-term consequences for
essentially perennial questions like how
do perception learning attention and
sensation all work together
and under what imperative might they
work together
and then the authors provide a very
preliminary discussion that they're
going to go into more later
about how predictive coding matters for
machine learning
and so they write predictive coding
proposes that using a simple
unsupervised lost function
such as simply attempting to predict
incoming sensory data
is sufficient to develop a complex
general and hierarchically rich
representations of the world
they're suggesting that this has found
support in the successes of modern
machine learning models that are trained
on unsupervised predictive or
auto-regressive objectives
so here's some of the papers that they
cite this is the brown at all and the
kaplan at all
and these both have to do with the
training of what are increasingly
becoming important modern machine
learning methods which are the language
models
in contrast to modern machine learning
algorithms which are trained to end with
a global loss at the output
so given the total big data set give me
the lowest total error on the whole data
set
in predictive coding prediction errors
are computed at every layer which means
that each layer only has to focus on
minimizing local errors than global loss
this property potentially enables
predictive coding to learn in a
biologically plausible way using only
local and hebian learning rules and this
is going to connect to calm and
filtering and pid control
so they're kind of
laying out the land and showing where
they're going to connect in the
introduction very very qualitatively and
then again we're gonna zoom back down to
find out what's happening at one level
of predictive coding and then try to
rebuild some of the formalisms related
to calm and filtering and pid control
and the bigger questions that people
might be curious about asking would be
like what does it mean
for computation to be biologically
inspired
what is possible when we're thinking
about some of the similarities and
differences and complementarities
between biological and different kinds
of conventional and unconventional
computation
the next
part
maria please take it away i'll be
changing slides so thanks a lot for
adding a lot of the historical context
and looking forward to learning about
what you have to share here
okay
so uh this is actually uh the paragraph
that is in the paper
okay that they
start talking about the history of
predictive coding so
while predictive coding as a
neuroscientific theory originated in the
80s and 90s with montford rao and
ballard
uh sure
nevison
or something
laughlin and dubs
and was first developed into its modern
mathematical form and comprehensive
theory of cortical responses in the mid
2000s with freestyle it has deep
intellectual anticipates
these precursors include helmholtz
notion of perception as an unconscious
inference and kant's notion that a
priory structure is needed to make sense
of sensory dictum okay
and as well as early ideas of
compression and feedback control in
cybernetics and information theory
and on the next slides i will be talking
a little bit more about history and
philosophy of predictive coding
and then some core formalisms and
various generalizations and elaborations
of predictive coding
if there is anything you want to say
daniel just feel free to jump in okay
so
uh the historical and philosophical
background of perception is huge okay
however seeing in the context of
predictive coding framework authors
usually come up with a similar reasoning
about perception
and
then we can start thinking uh with the
greek philosopher plato on his allegory
of the cave
uh from
514 to 520 before christ
which he said
basically that some people would be
trapped in a cave forever watching
shadows cast by objects moving near a
fire behind them
and then they would like be there
forever have children that would grow
like that
inside the cave and you know eventually
these shadows
uh from the objects near fire behind
them would be
the real thing and the only thing for
these people they wouldn't believe that
there is anything outside the cave so
this this would be it these shadows
would be the only thing okay so what
plato would claim here is that our own
conscious perceptions are just like
these shadows okay meaning that they are
indirect reflections of hidden causes
that we can never directly encounter
and
but
a few centuries later the arab medieval
scholar al al hasan
wrote a lot of interesting notes on
visual perception actually he wrote
six
volumes if i'm not mistaken in uh of his
book of optics
where he explored the view that human
perception often depends on mechanisms
of judgment and inference instead of you
know providing access traits to the
world so
you can see that uh
very early in the in our western
thinking we have this
notion that we do not have
direct access to the world okay that
there is some inference
going on
okay
great all right so
jumping to the 18th century
we can find two important philosophers
okay the english david hume and the
german emmanuel cut
him in 1739 to 1740
export the inductive inferences and
causation
the problem of induction that he brought
was an analysis of cause and effect and
perception and the conclusion
that he gets is that all our mental life
could be traced back to the effects of
sense experience because since we do not
have
direct contact with the world we could
never have one-to-one relationship with
the objects there and therefore
it is possible to have one effect with
many possible causes and one cause it
with
effects
the solution here would be then
extracting statistical regularities and
imagining what happens when the world is
intervened upon a controlled manner as
the philosopher jacob howie developed
developed in his book the predictive
mind in 2014
equally important
uh
in the critique of pure reason in 1781
kant
will add an important element to this
story among you know countless other
elements to the story he will add that
the brain uses
existing information regarding space and
time to make sense of the chaotic
sensory data it constantly receives
to provide an organism the perception as
they know
so
uh all of these
scholars would tell us
right in the early ages that
we do not have direct access to the
things in the world
and we need pre-existing information to
make sense of all the data we constantly
receive
lots of predictive coding stuff
it really makes me wonder why it's
sometimes still so
ineffable or poorly understood or even
seen as controversial
some of these perspectives which have
been
[Music]
as you
are describing like
thought of and convergently come to for
many thousands of years in different
cultures so really interesting
yes
and
well in the late 19th century the german
scientist hermann from helmholtz in 1860
depicted perception as
uh involving probabilistic influence
yeah he he is one of our gods
and communities
but and he was really inspired by kant
okay
uh
and
with that inspiration he developed the
idea of the brain as a hypothesis tester
and that perception is a process of
unconscious inference okay
and more specifically this idea that he
developed
in experiments was that perception has
to be inferred by combining sensory
signals with the brain expectations and
beliefs about their causes
and such inferences happen
without the subject's awareness i mean
it has to happen without the subject's
awareness because
you know imagine all the chaotic sensory
data coming
and you open your eyes and you have to
try to organize everything i mean it
doesn't happen that way you just open
your eyes and
everything is still stable
and so uh it's unconscious and
it needs to keep track of the causes in
the world by updating perceptual best
guesses or you can say hypothesis as new
sensory signals arrive
so here he built
uh
the idea
that we use combini we use sensory
signals
with the brain expectations to
you know update
the hypothesis we make upon we make for
the causes
of the effects we receive in the world
and this means that he somehow turned
humes and inside scientifical
claiming that we can only infer things
out there in a word behind a sensory
veil which if i'm not mistaken will be
eventually called mark of blackness
is that right then
not sure uh
maybe unveiled
how hot was crucial to many different
works in machine learning one that was
even nicely named as helmholtz machine
he was crucial in psychology
neuroscience cognitive science and so on
particularly in psychology helmholtz
inside inspired yuri schneizer in 1967
and later richard gregory in 1980 and
eve arvind rock in 1983 to develop the
analysis by synthesis approach which is
the process that analyze a signal or
image by reproducing
it using a model
there there's a picture of nicest
analysis based into this approach
some schema available in this link
and in fact
gregory built some kind of neural
hypothesis testing model based on his
how hot c and understanding of the brain
as continually formulating perceptual
hypothesis about the word and testing
them by acquiring data
from sensory organs
okay so many things happened after the
analysis by synthesis stuff but
i will just jump to what we have in
philosophy today because
we will touch the formalisms and the
computation stuff afterwards okay so i
will just make a jump and go to what we
have in philosophy today
so
uh
recent works in philosophy and cognitive
neuroscience have contributed to the
expansive predictive coding framework
and the beijing paradigm in the brain
and many of the seminal works we have in
the field addresses predictive coding as
predictive processing
without
you know any relevant difference in the
first
instance
and
well
for instance the philosophy jacob howie
that is based in monash university of
australia
aimed to the amazon improvement of
predictionary minimization mechanism and
the concept of winning hypothesis for
conscious perception
also he is interested in what pp
predictive processing studies can bring
to people with mental disorders such as
autism and schizophrenia actually the
three of them
of the philosophers here are interested
in what people can bring to to
improvement in psychiatry and medicine
uh in general so in 2014 he published an
important textbook on the matter that is
the predictive mind the red book you can
see
where he tries to solve the problem of
perception
inspired on humans induction problem
with bayesian inference and predictive
processing
later in 2016 the philosopher andy clark
based on university of sussex england
carefully developed what he called
action-oriented predictive processing in
his book surfing uncertainty where he
adds and advances the crucial role of
action in our perception
and he makes a lot of interesting
connections between recent works in
computational neuroscience and
artificial intelligence
and his eclectic philosophy of might
and last year in 2021 the neuroscientist
and usf one of the authors of this paper
we were talking here
uh and also by the university of sussex
made an amazing contribution to the
fields with his book being you where he
claims that we are beast machines whose
perception is a controlled hallucination
and he improves consciousness
descriptions using predictive processing
framework and establishing the real
problem of consciousness that in his own
words requires explaining why a
particular pattern of brain activity or
other physical process
maps to a particular kind of conscious
experience not merely establishing that
it's this
two you know philosophers and scientists
work on
and
they
here they are
okay right so
i
was talking about predictive coding and
then i went to predictive processing is
there a difference
well many authors
would use the the terms freely okay but
then i found clark saying in his book
uh the difference that he understands
from predictive coding to predictive
processing so he puts
as the fact that predictive processing
is not simply the use of the data
compression strategy known as predictive
coding rather it is the use of that
strategy in the very special context of
hierarchical multi-level
systems deploying probabilistic
generative models
such systems exhibit powerful forms of
learning and deliver rich forms of
context sensitive processing and are
able uh flexibly to combine top-down and
bottom-up flows of information within
multi-layer cascade
predictive processing does combine the
use within a multi-level by
bi-directional cascade of top-down
probabilistic general models
with the core predictive coding strategy
of efficient encoding and transmission
okay
from this
i'm not sure if you agree with me daniel
but
reading this
this paragraph makes me wonder i mean
okay predictive coding is a local uh
bottom up top down cascade and stuff but
it also is
multi-layer
yes it also has some hierarchy so
i'm not sure what what he mean i mean
i'm not sure if i understand
the difference between predictive coding
and predictive processing as he puts
yeah very insightful
and it made me think about the
difference between like coding like
programming and like data coding like
python coding for data and data
processing which is a little bit like it
could be multiple computer languages and
so you're really highlighting something
important which is that when the data
are compressed according to a strategy
where the errors are being transmitted
rather than the actual sort of estimate
itself that's like that information
channel is in a predictive coding way
and then this helps us
use predictive processing
for like the bigger picture for systems
that implement predictive coding modules
but that's not like the only module
they're deploying so that that'll be
something cool to like hear people's
perspective on really nice um
distinction here though
yep
and
okay so i wrote something here that
just like was you said that maybe uh
coding would be better to use for
formalisms and implementations and
processing for the philosophical
understanding that prediction is the
basis of a signal interpretation
eg as opposed to descriptive
okay
so
uh jumping back to
formalism
uh predictive coding and information
theory and signal processing okay so
another deep intellectual influence in
predictive coding comes from information
theory from channel in 1948
and especially the minimum redundancy
principle of barlow in 1961 89 and 61.
two
information theory tell us that
information is inseparable from a lack
of predictability
if something is predictable before
observing it it cannot give us much
information i loved this sentence
conversely to maximize the rate of
information transfer the message must be
minimally predictable and enhance
minimally redundant
predictive coding as a means to remove
redundancy in a signal was first applied
in signal processing
where it was used to reduce transmission
bandwidth
for video transmission
and
do you want to say something i'll just
describe this without reading it it was
a a common uh and effective although it
can be improved on by other methods
it's a method for video encoding known
as frame differencing where basically uh
one frame gets described and then
subsequent frames only the pixels that
change have to be described
so that is a lot like an analogy to
predictive coding
in the sense that
it's able to connect the differences
between subsequent time steps and use
that to give really only the informative
pieces like i have a 100 digit number
and then i'm just going to tell you the
third digit changed now it's an 8
instead of having to repeat the same
number and then 99 of those digits
they're informative like in the sense
that they're good info it's true
but they're not informative in the
information theory context because they
were quite predictable before observing
it
okay
and so initial schemes used a simple
approach of subtracting the new to be
transmitted frame from the old frame in
effect using a trivial prediction that
the new frame is always the same as the
old frame which works well in reducing
bandwidth in many settings where there
are only few objects moving in the video
against this
static background
and more advanced methods often predict
each new frame using a number of past
frames weighted by some coefficient
an approach known as linear predictive
coding
okay
so now
predictive coding in the eye
and the brain
the first concrete discussion of
predictive coding in the neurosystem
arose as a model of neural properties of
the retina
with
srinivasin 1982.
specifically as a model of
center surrounded cells
which fire when presented with either a
light spot against a dark background on
center of surround or alternatively a
dark spot against a light background of
center on surround cells
it was argued that this coding scheme
helps to minimize redundancy in the
visual scheme specifically by removing
the spatial redundancy in natural visual
scenes
that the intensity of
one pixel helps predict quite well the
intensity of neighboring pixels
and then the first picture related to it
uh do you want to talk about it or just
um we're just going to look at two
different tissues of the nervous system
that have some predictive elements
and this is referring to some of the
photosensitive cells that are on the
retina and that's work that had been
done
qualitatively and empirically for
hundreds of years but then was connected
to predictive perspectives in the 80s
and then we're also going to look as
you'll now unpack at what's happening in
the cortex of the brain amongst
different layers
with month fruit in 1992 was perhaps the
first to extend this theory of the
retina and the
lgn to a fully fledged general theory of
cortical function
his theory was motivated by simple
observations about the neurophysiology
of cortical cortical connections
specifically the existence of separate
feet forward and feed back paths where
the feet forward path is originated in
the superficial layers of the cortex and
the feedback pathways originated
primarily primarily
in the deep layers
great so we kind of had this philosophy
development happening over thousands of
years
and then in the 1900s people were
starting to connect the neuroanatomy and
the histology
to some of these predictive ideas and
then now let's kind of close the loop
and bring it back to the critical work
that fristen highlighted in his 2018
paper
yep and how predictive coding in the
brain gets computational mathematical
while montford's theory contained most
aspects of classical predictive coding
theory in the cortex
it was not a compound accompanied by any
simulations or empirical work and so
it's potential as a framework for
understanding the cortex was not fully
appreciated
and so again the seminal work of raw and
ballard in 1999
had its impact precisely by doing this
and so they created a small predictive
coding network
according to the principles
i'm sorry
uh they created a small predictive
coding network according to the
principles identified by mumford and
empirically investigated its behavior
demonstrating that the complex and
dynamic interplay of predictions and
prediction errors could explain several
otherwise perplexing
neurophysiological phenomena
specifically extracurricular receptive
field effects such as and stopping
neurons
yeah this is pretty interesting because
even the idea that the neurons that are
active while a certain stimuli is being
presented that those are neurons that
are receptive
to that stimuli that's within the
paradigm of signal reception
and then it's like there's classical
signal reception you know the pitcher
throws the ball the catcher catches the
ball it's classic
but unfortunately or not there's all
these so-called extra classical effects
and so this paper proposed a simple
architecture that was able to encompass
the so-called classical as well as some
of the important extra classical
effects under this predictive processing
framework and so that really led to a
lot of developments in neuroscience in
the last 20 plus years
and that's exactly what we're going to
go into now so thanks for providing that
awesome context like it really
helps
i think situate some of the details that
we're about to look into
okay so let's get a little technical
what happened after
round ballard's 1999 synthesis so
remember that carl fristen said that
that was like one of those once in a
decade papers for him so how did he
change his action selection publication
policies after reading that paper well
anyone can guess but what fristen did
was that he cast the predictive coding
algorithm
as approximate bayesian inference
upon gaussian generative models
and this is going to be connected this
is all in the paper for people to read
but this connects
basically all of the previous themes
that we had been talking about
like the information theory minimum
redundancy and the helmholtzian idea of
perception as inference come together
in the bayesian perspective
on the predictive coding architecture by
rao and ballard
so
the authors write firstens approach
reformulates the mostly heuristic
round ballard model in the language of
variational bayesian inference which
we're going to look more at
and fristen showed that the energy
function in rao and ballard
can be understood as a variational free
energy of the kind that is minimized
through variational inference
so that really connected the dots
between
predictive coding architectures and the
empirical biological findings to all
this work on variational bayesian
inference
and those are the 2003 5 and 8 single
author papers by carl
so
what is variational
and bayesian and variational bayesian
approaches and we're just going to look
at the author's words and there's many
many awesome places to look
for educational materials and also check
out some of the live streams like 26 32
34 37 and 39
so to be brief about it the authors
write
variational inference approximates an
intractable inference problem
with a tractable optimization problem so
like a super hard problem to solve just
by thinking about it and then guessing
at the right answer
with a tractable optimization problem so
it's like 20 questions it's going to be
hard to guess on your first question but
if you take this iterative optimization
approach maybe there's a way to actually
resolve it so it's not exactly like that
but it's like kind of again flipping out
something that's hard to solve in one
shot with an approach
and this iterative gradient descent type
improvement that actually gets you to a
good solution
and so this is where we're going to
introduce some of the variables and the
letters that we're going to use
following a lot of perceptual work in
bayesian statistics we're going to use o
for observations which are like data
either the actual data that the sensor
provides us or generated data of the
kind that we would expect the sensor to
give us and then x
are the latent or the unobserved states
of the system so like x would be the
temperature in the room and o is what
the thermometer reading is
and that's sort of a bayesian approach
that helps us have a generative model of
the data generating process which is
also known as the joint distribution
because it is jointly over both the
observations and the latent states
where variational inference comes into
play
um is that
is hinted at in this paragraph on base
so in order to do exact base
one would have to
find this normalizing factor
however that can be intractable because
it requires basically integrating or
summing over all latent variable states
and that's not always
easy or known
so the approach of the variational
method
is aiming to
approximate the posterior
using an auxiliary posterior
using a different set of parameters
phi
so the q
is going to be reflecting like the
distribution the variational
distribution that we control
that is of like a family of functions
that is more
amenable to optimization so p could be
like a super messy function but q is
going to be constructed
by the modeler to be a lot simpler
and so it is going to have its own
parameters and those parameters phi
are mu
and sigma
and so
it's kind of like we would be interested
in the mean and the variance of the x
the actual temperature in the room given
the thermometer but what if it were too
hard to even get that
well what we might want to do would be
imagine that the temperature were
normally distributed like a gaussian
distribution
with this mean mu in the variance sigma
so even if the temperature in the room
weren't actually gaussian distributed
maybe it's approximately enough and so
the variational approach to the bayesian
method is to introduce this variational
distribution queue that's going to have
like a lot of good features moving
forward
here's how that cue comes into play
this equation one
is expressing using the variables that
we've seen
it's saying and also introducing this
divergence d so first just the
definition of d and then what this
formalism says
so d
of p and double line q so any double
line means between this and that d is a
function that measures the divergence
between two distributions so for example
p and q
and here the divergence is going to be
calculated as the kl divergence
although other divergences are possible
so in the divergence between the one
that we simplified and controlled q
and that intractable true posterior
if that divergence were minimized to
zero we would be like fitting
p as well as we could with q
and this is saying in one it's saying q
star the best q
of x the latent states given the data
and the variational parameters
so the best possible room temperature
prediction given thermometer readings
and variational parameters are
a minimization
over
all the variational parameters
of
the divergence between
the q distribution that we control of
exactly what we want the best answer for
and the p generative model of exactly
what would be the best to compute like
the temperature given the observations
on the thermometer
and so that goes a long way towards
rewriting an inference problem as a
diversions problem
but they write
however merely writing the problem this
way does not solve it because the
divergence that we need to optimize
still contains the intractable true
posterior so it's rewritten as a
divergence between like something we
control and something that we kind of
set out to do this because we couldn't
calculate it so we have
prepared it but still this is
intractable so this is not usable alone
they write the beauty of variational
inference is that it instead optimizes a
tractable upper bound on this divergence
called the variational free energy vfe
to generate the bound we apply bayes
rule to the true posterior to rewrite it
in the form of the generative model and
the evidence
so here's that p of x given o
that's rewritten as now not of x given o
but p of o comma x that's the joint
distribution divided by the observations
so this
by the bayes rule p of x given o is
equivalent to this that's why this is
the first line here
they provide some rewritings
and then they write in the third line
the expectation
around p of o so the actual likelihood
of the observations themselves like how
likely is the thermometer saying 21
it vanishes
since the expectation is over the
variable x which is not in p of o
so it's like what is the expectation of
this coin flip over the temperature
tomorrow it's like because they're
different variables
it makes them very easy to separate out
if we're only interested in one of them
and then they write that this f
the free energy
is a very is attractable quantity since
it's a divergence between two quantities
we assume that we as the modeler know
the variational approximate posterior q
of x given o that's the distribution
that we control and the generative joint
distribution p of o comma x
so we traded out this intractable true
posterior where it's like if we knew it
then we would just stop there but we
don't know it so we've traded it out for
a divergence between something that we
totally control
q of x conditioned on these other
parameters
and
a joint distribution which we might have
uncertainty over but at least can be
modeled
so that's one of the key pieces of
variational bays and that's not specific
to predictive coding it's just an
important way that the authors are
introducing it here
anything to add
all right so let's kind of continue on
this theme
since f is an upper bound by minimizing
f we derive the variational distribution
that we control closer to the true
posterior
as an additional bonus
under certain conditions
f can be used for model selection so
that means it can be used not just to
kind of fine-tune a model that we've
already chosen but it can actually do
choosing from parametrically or
structurally different models
they write we can gain an important
intuition about f by showing it can be
decomposed into a likelihood
maximization term
and the kl divergence term which
penalizes deviation from the bayesian
prior these terms are often called
accuracy and complexity and this
decomposition is often used in different
machine learning algorithms so that's
one
rewriting
of free energy as this divergence
between the q and the p
and then rewriting that as an accuracy
and a complexity which we'll go into
maybe more another time
and
they write in many practical cases we
must relax the assumption that we know
the generative model
p of o and x the joint distribution
luckily this is not fatal
instead it is possible to learn the
generative model alongside the
variational posterior on the fly
and in parallel using
expectation maximization
so
this is basically the alternation
shown by equations three
of how we can be
setting one side of this kl divergence
fixed and optimizing the other side and
then going back and doing it the other
way and so that kind of back and forth
expectation maximization we're going to
be like reducing this divergence from
both sides
and so formalism three are saying the
variational parameters
phi
at the next time step t point t plus one
are an optimization
argument
of those parameters
um holding
the theta constant
and then
the second part of informalism three is
the exact opposite
now the generative model parameters
theta at t plus one are minimization
over
literally the same thing but holding the
variational parameters constant so
there's a lot more to say about
expectation maximization but this is
like
converging to a
small divergence
by whittling away at both sides and kind
of alternating there so that's how
expectation maximization can be used as
a heuristic algorithm for variational
bayesian optimization
how do we go from variational inference
which all of those previous slides are
things that we've basically talked about
before and that are not applying to
predictive coding specifically so how
are we going to get to predictive coding
they write having reviewed the general
principles of variational inference we
can see how they relate to predictive
coding
first to make any variational inference
algorithm concrete we must specify the
forms of the variational posterior and
the generative model it's like if you
want to do formalism three
those are the two pieces you need you
need like the phi stuff and the theta
stuff
and so they specify it here
n means a normal distribution
with like a mean comma variance format
and so they're going to define
a gaussian form for the generative model
the mean of this likelihood gaussian is
assumed to be some function of hidden
states which can be parameterized with
theta
while the mean of the prior gaussian
distribution is going to be a g of mu so
we're going to have like f of theta
and g of mu
the variances of these two gaussian
distributions of the generative model
are sigma 1 and sigma 2.
this is a slight technical detail but
they're going to assume that the
variational posterior is a drock delta
which is like a spiking function
distribution that's centered at the mean
however they explore that differently
with laplace assumption
so this is basically taking what we
discussed about variational inference
and preparing it to be entered into a
predictive coding way
so they're setting up the problem with
which parameters you're going to want to
do variational inference on in order to
implement predictive coding
and there's of course more to say but
we're just giving a first pass
in in appendix a
is where they describe the difference
between
using the laplacian approximation and
the direct delta so it's footnote 8
which suggests moving to appendix a
and looking at the buckley 2017 for a
walk through
but this on the bottom right is kind of
like a summary of the difference between
the dirac delta approach and the laplace
method approach so the diroc delta is
like we're trying to find the spike
that's at the mean
or the median there's some other details
in play
that
is where the bulk of the probability
distribution mass is
whereas the laplace method tries to fit
a polynomial
like just a second degree polynomial
like a quadratic
over
the probability distribution
also in the way that
is best fitting so there's some
similarities and some differences and
it's explored more in the buckley 2017
paper
on the fep for action perception
mathematical review
so let's continue with our
exploration of how we do variational
bays and make it a predictive coding
model
at the top they write we define the
prediction errors epsilon o
that's like the error on observation
and epsilon x
that's the error on the mean states so
the epsilon o
is like
o minus f
of some function you know f of some
parameters and then there's also the
epsilon x so how
much prediction error do you have about
the observation how much prediction
error do you have about the hidden state
epsilons are the prediction errors and
they're parameterized by these theta 1
and 2 variances
given all of this we can derive
dynamics for all the variables of
interest so that's the actual underlying
hidden state the temperature in the room
that we want to be
actually predicting mu
and then well the variational parameter
of it
and then
theta one and theta two which are the
variances you can think of it as like
the variance of the room temperature and
the variance of the term of the
thermometer i hope that's not
wrong or an oversimplification but those
are like the two variances
and we want the real temperature of the
room
they write we can derive dynamics for
all these variables of interest by
taking the derivatives of the
variational free energy f
the update rules are as follows
and so this is change in mu theta 1 and
theta 2 over time d mu dt d theta 1 over
dt and d theta 2 over dt
and that has some equivalences with some
f's so it's going to be going from just
the change in the mu estimate through
time to something involving free energy
and then that's defined more formally
importantly these update rules are very
similar to the ones derived in rao and
ballard 1999 and therefore can be
interpreted as recapitulating core
predictive coding update rules
for instance the muse are typically
interpreted as rapidly changing neural
firing rates while thetas are slowly
changing synaptic weight values
so they're weaving together connecting
the biology with the formalisms here
and they write also that that mu can be
understood as the process of perception
that's like how hot is it in the room
since mu is meant to correspond to the
estimate of the latent state of the
environment generating the observations
on the thermometer and by contrast the
dynamics of thetas can be thought of as
corresponding to learning
since theta effectively defined the
mapping between the latent state and the
observations
so it's like you think you know how the
thermometer is related to the
temperature in the room
and then you see your thermometer
changing you're changing how hot you
think the room is that happens over a
shorter time scale and then over a
longer time scale you might come to
learn the variability of a temperature
or how noisy the thermometer is but
that's more like learning
than perception however they're on a
continuum using this model
so actually this up to formalism 9
completes the core formalism of
predictive coding which is it's a
variational bayesian approach to having
this ongoing prediction error minimizing
approach to latent state estimation that
is the heart of predictive coding
and now we're going to jump into like a
few different elaborations that we're
going to be moving through a little bit
more quickly
anything to add maria
awesome
the previous examples
focused on predictive coding with a
single level of latent variables mu 1.
however the expressiveness of such a
scheme is limited
deep neural networks in machine learning
have demonstrated that having
hierarchical sets of latent variables is
a key to enabling methods that learn
powerful abstractions
and handle intrinsically hierarchical
dynamics of the sort that humans
intuitively perceive
predictive coding schemes introduced can
be straightforwardly extended to handle
hierarchical dynamics of arbitrary depth
equivalent to deep neural networks in
machine learning
this is done through postulating
multiple layers of latent variables x
sub 1 through x sub l and then defining
the generative model as follows
so like p the generative model
is going to be basically over all the
layers
so just as the generative model
and the variational distribution had to
be defined for the single layer model
here they're going to define the p
distribution and now they need the q
we define a separate variational
posterior for each layer so they define
the p's and the cues
just like they did in the single layer
and then that allows them to calculate
the variational free energy which is a
sum of the prediction errors of each
level
and so
this is f now not just over one layer
but multiple levels
so the variational posteriors that need
to be calculated are partitioned across
the layers
which allows them to be summed
in a very straightforward way
given that free energy divides nicely
into the sum of layer wise prediction
errors
it comes as no surprise the dynamics of
the mu and the theta are similarly
separable across layers
that allows different layers of this
prediction hierarchy to be like precise
or imprecise
and allow those movements to happen in a
way that's
uncorrelated which is not just because
the real world presents itself with
settings where there's like confidence
at lower and higher and vice versa but
it makes this calculation of the free
energy of the whole system
more like a simple sum whereas if there
was these like really complex
interactions with the first layer by the
third layer if the fifth layer is this
way then
doing the statistics would be a lot more
challenging
so visually here's what that looks like
we have the mu which is the mean
estimate
of what's happening at that level
and then
there's passing of these epsilon error
terms
so they write this is the architecture
of a in figure 1 multi-layer predictive
coding network
shown here with two value and error
neurons in each layer
the value neurons project to the error
neurons of the layer below
and the error neurons represent the
current activity so this is like
starting to walk us back towards that
cortical layout
where there's a cortical column
where there's some so-called upwards and
downward signaling but also there's
lateral signaling
so this is a graphical model
that's reflecting
the way that predictive coding
can be arranged almost like in series
and in parallel
to have like wide models
and deep models just like you could have
a neural network where it was
four neurons four neurons four neurons
four neurons or you could have 64 and
then 64. that would be like a shallower
but wider model and so that notion of
shallowness and depth is also going to
come into play with predictive coding
here we're in formalism 12 and 13.
and so now we're looking at the
rate of change the derivative of mu sub
l
so the estimate of the mean at that
layer and theta l the variance at that
layer so these are the update rules the
gradients
for the mean and the variance of
different levels and they're also
written as free energy functionals of
those layers
and
the dynamics of the variational means
depends only on the prediction errors at
their layer and the prediction errors on
the layer below so again we don't have
this epsilon at l minus 1 connecting up
all the way to mu it's only through
these local connections within and
between layers by which we're needing to
calculate anything
we can think of the muse as trying to
compromise between causing error
by deviating from the prediction from
the layer above
and adjusting their own prediction to
resolve error at the layer below so it's
kind of like a hierarchy of of bosses or
tasks and there's like top-down
expectations and there's the bottom-up
reality which might be like ahead or
behind schedule and then it puts each
person like in this compromise
situation
crucially for conceptual readings of
predictive coding
and this is where there's like a doorway
to the philosophy and some of the
broader discussions
this means that sensory data is not
directly transmitted up through the
hierarchy as is assumed in much of
perceptual neuroscience
and so it totally returns us to these
questions like what is perception what
is cognition what is action
what what is
coming from the eye to the brain or what
goes from the brain to the eye what is
the eye doing what is the brain doing
with respect to the eye
and how does it relate to predictive
coding
any quick answers on those
naturally
cool so
after introducing that kernel of the
predictive coding formalism and taking
it into the multi-level context now we
can look at another elaboration or
generalization
so they write in 2.3
we have considered the modeling of just
a single static stimulus up
however most interesting data that the
brain receives comes in temporal
sequences o bar which is o through time
to model such temporal sequences it's
often useful to split the latent
variables into states which can vary
with time and parameters which cannot
in the case of sequences
instead of minimizing the variational
free energy we must instead minimize the
free action which is the path integral
of the variational free energy through
time
we're not going to go into the
formalisms
related to the generalized coordinates
or 14 15 16 and 17
but it's something that we can explore
later
and just as a reminder just to kind of
um
excite somebody who might want to
explore it
we explored the idea of the generalized
coordinates of motion a lot in active
livestream number 26 with decosta at all
and so here was a model where we have
from left to right time at different
time steps
and then there's the observables of
something
and then it is part of this like column
of higher derivatives of its motion so
it's like position its
velocity its acceleration and so on and
so at each time step
moving forward you're computing the
generalized coordinates of motion
for like the movement of a baseball and
that is what ties generalized
coordinates of motion to pid control
which will also come back at the end
also known as integrator chains and this
is all happening within this discussion
of bayesian mechanics just like if we
had been talking about the baseball we
would be talking about physical
mechanics or statistical mechanics well
it's bayesian so it's bayesian mechanics
and the physics of action and control
that's what they explore in section 2-3
section 2.4 introduces and goes into a
little bit more detail on precision
one core aspect of predictive coding
absent in the original rao and ballard
1999 formulation
is the notion of precision
or inverse variance
so precision and variance are like one
over each other so if someone said it's
very high precision that's a very narrow
very sharp distribution
and one over the variance is another way
to write that so sometimes it's used
with like a beta and a gamma in other
models
precision serve to multiplicatively
modulate
the importance of the prediction errors
and thus possess a significant influence
in the overall dynamics of the model
and so
we won't go into every detail with how
the precisions are themselves fit but
just wanted to note that this big sigma
is the free energy being summed over the
layers
so big sigma
is a um is a multiplicative sum
sorry it's just a sum
but then this smaller sigma inside
is sigma as the precision matrix at a
given level
so it's kind of like different uses of
sigma
but this is a way where the variances
and the prediction errors at a given
level
are being summed across levels and
that's helping fit these precision terms
statistical detail but it's important
for making it work in real inference
okay
in section 2.5 they they pull back from
elaborating on predictive coding and
they talk more about how it has some
biologically plausible bases
so this was quite interesting
while technically predictive coding is
simply variational inference and
filtering algorithm under gaussian
assumptions from the beginning it has
been claimed to be biologically
plausible theory of cortical computation
and also for other brain regions like
the i
and for other cognitive systems
the literature has consistently drawn
close connections between the theory and
potential computations that may be
performed in brains for example rao and
ballard explicitly claimed to model the
early visual cortex
and fristen explicitly proposed
predictive coding as a general theory of
cortical computation this is like the
realism and instrumentalism discussion
are we just modeling
these systems and the kind of data that
they provide us
and it just fits really well as a model
but we're not saying that the
architecture of the statistical model
has anything to do with the architecture
of the physical pieces of the brain
or is it a little bit in the gray zone
where it's kind of like wow that model
fits so well
and the anatomy looks so good maybe
there's something there to it
and so in this section they review
empirical work that has attempted to
validate or falsify key tenets of
predictive coding in the cortex
as well as some issues with the approach
so it's mainly focused on the mammalian
brain and the neural cell type
but
as always we can sort of think about
what is
the adjacent here like what are the
roles of other cell types in predictive
coding in the mammalian brain
and then how might like the insect
nervous system or how my other nervous
systems or non-nervous systems perform
predictive coding
and then they just provide
one example
where they take what they had shown in
figure one
with this multi-level predictive coding
scheme
that was sort of
predictively programming as they say
one to think about cortical cognition
and now they're gonna make that
connection clear in figure two so on the
right side is there figure two
and that's the canonical micro circuit
model of bostos at all
mapped on to the connectivity of a
cortical region
and so then in red are those parameters
that we've been discussing the muse and
the epsilons the means and then the
prediction errors
and then
here's just a few other representations
of what others have written
about like that cortical column
so here's like an evolutionary
perspective that connects some of the
mammalian cortex with the avian
pallium brain region
and so just the way that people work out
these kinds of circuit diagrams
like by looking at the actual tissue
and then here's the statistics and so
how does the tissue
relate to
the statistical model but that's what
they explore in figure 2.
okay any thoughts
ok
in section 3
they continue to review empirical work
but with more of a focus on machine
learning
of the unsupervised and supervised
setting
and they're going to also explore how
the predictive coding architecture can
be made more biologically plausible by
relaxing certain assumptions implicit in
this canonical model
and introduce action into the picture
figure three
they summarize a few different what they
call paradigms of predictive coding
summary of the input output
relationships for each paradigm of
predictive coding
so it's the input and the prediction the
output of different paradigms
so here's the classical predictive
coding
in observation data are coming in
predictions about those observations are
coming out it's an instantaneous
real-time snapshot
the real-time anticipatory unfolding is
still getting data as input
but it's predicting the observation at
the next time step which is a similar
problem to predicting it at this time
step but it's like a little bit
different
that can happen not just through time
but also in the context of space with
like a spatial predictive coding
and then these two on the right
supervised predictive coding in the
generative and in the discriminative
direction
have to do with the relationship with
reading in labels
and giving out observations
or vice versa
make me a cat
here's a picture of a cat
here's a picture
that's a cat
so these are some of the ways that
predictive coding models have been
applied
3.1 they explore the
way that unsupervised training relates
to predictive coding
so that is machine learning on unlabeled
data like here's
a hundred thousand hours of human
speaking learn how to speak that's like
an unsupervised approach whereas the
supervised approach would be here's a
thousand hours of human speaking here's
a thousand hours of a river here's a
thousand hours of you know of some other
noise and so by the label
then the algorithm would learn what is
speech versus non-speech versus the
unsupervised but there's also a lot of
like continuum and complexity and it's a
whole topic
um in
some of the sub sections of 3.1 they go
a little bit deeper
into the
temporal
predictive and the auto encoding aspects
but we're not gonna go into those right
now
in figure four in section three two
they look at supervised predictive
coding and look at it in that forwards
and backwards direction
and so here they're looking at the
classic mnist data set for
evaluation where there's some pictures
of handwritten digits and then it's
predicting and so here's the
generative predictive coding and the
discriminative direction
where here the data are coming in like
the picture of the five with the pixel
intensities
and that is relating to the more high
level estimate of it being a five so
this is observation in
label out that's a five
here's label in
pixels reflecting it out
so that's connecting machine learning to
predictive coding
in section 3-3
they're also exploring some
relaxed predictive coding
and it has to do with relaxing certain
mathematical assumptions that they
had introduced earlier for simplicity
and for clarity
we're not going to
go into it but it has to do
with
making it more
useful in the real world by relaxing
certain assumptions
and then in three four
they
uh
explore deep predictive code
so they write so far in this review
we've only considered direct variations
on the fristen round bollard models of
predictive coding which are relatively
pure
and use only local biologically
plausible learning rules
there also exists a small literature
experimenting with these models often
achieve better performance on more
challenging tasks than the purer models
can achieve so pure again here meaning
that it uses only local biologically
plausible learning rules so only
connected entities locally
and so
these models they suggest provide a
vital threat of evidence about scaling
properties and performance of deep and
complex predictive coding networks
and
they write the first major work in this
area is prednet
which uses multiple layers of recurrent
convolutional lstms neural networks to
implement a deep predictive coding
network
so here is what
prednet looked like
this is the original prednet
architecture
and so they have convolutional lstms
that are passing information in a
top-down
way and in a bottom-up way
so maybe we could look at it more later
and then i also just
found this 2019 2020 paper um where they
also explored like whether prednet
actually is doing predictive coding but
again a whole another rabbit hole
so section three
reviewed through figure three and some
discussions on the subsections a few of
the different paradigms and the ways
this predictive coding architecture has
been applied
in section 4 they're going to connect it
to other algorithms so we're going to
basically speed through all of the
connections except for active inference
first they connect predictive coding in
section 41 to the back propagation of
error
this is really important like for neural
network training
but we're not going to talk about it
here but it sounds like really
interesting to discuss
one that we'll introduce but then skip
over most of the details is the
relationship between linear predictive
coding and calm and filtering so we can
remember that the linear predictive
coding is not just the frame
differencing it's where there's like
that coefficient of how much you should
forget each of the previous frames
and this is known in signal processing
as the kalman filter
the column filter as this slide shows
is an iterative mathematical process to
quickly estimate true values position
and velocity so that's also like getting
towards the generalized coordinates of
motion and so the x's are like our
observations that's the thermometer
and then here's the red
is our calm and filtered temperature
unfolding through time
so our initial estimate gets quickly
corrected and then even though there's a
lot of noise in the observations
the kalman filter is like giving a good
prediction on the actual temperature
and this has been implemented in a ton
of bayesian approaches it's a totally
standard signal processing bayesian
approach
and in the following sections in 4.2
they have a lot of formalisms
about the kalman filter
and in appendix d they provide even more
formalisms on the kalman filter
so we're not going to really go into
either of those
in section 4.3
they introduced this idea of
normalization and normalizing flows
and so they wrote
the deep link between predictive coding
and normalization has been extended by
mourinho 2020
by situating predictive coding with
general recipe for building or
representing a complex distribution from
a simple intractable one
so we encourage people to look at this
merino 2020 paper if they want to learn
more about predictive coding variational
auto encoders and biological connections
but not going to discuss today
one other model that they connect
predictive coding to
is known as the biased competition model
and
that is unpacked in 4.4 but
i just wanted to pull up one example of
this biased competition model
and so this is from the sprottling paper
of 2008
within each processing stage nodes
compete to be active in response to the
current pattern of feed-forward activity
received from the sensory input or
previous processing stage so
it's like there's competitions amongst
the sub units to be activated by certain
kinds of inputs
and then there's some technical details
okay
now finally to active inference as we're
near the end of the discussion
this will be a little fun to explore
also in the coming weeks of course so
they write
in 4.5 predictive coding can also be
extended to include action
allowing for predictive coding agents to
undertake adaptive actions without any
major change to their fundamental
algorithms
the key insight is to note there are two
ways of minimizing prediction errors
the first is to update predictions to
match sensory data which corresponds to
classical perception
i thought that the ball was going to be
here but i guess it's over here
perception
the second is to take actions in the
world to force the incoming sensory data
to match the prediction
i'm going to move the ball to where i
expect it to be
or i expected the ball to be in the left
side of my visual field
so i'm going to move my eyes to the
right
so that it's in the left side of my
visual field so it's action is not
always like reaching out and moving the
ball
it can also be the action of choosing
where to look for example
and this is what is really fascinating
because we spent so long in the earlier
sections in the first 50 equations you
know
without action
so it's like oh no are there going to be
like another 250 equations with action
coming into the picture
but actually it's quite a simple
introduction
the basic approach to including action
in predictive coding is to minimize the
variational free energy with respect to
action
although free energy is not explicitly a
function of action it can be made so
implicitly
by noticing the dependence of sensory
observations on actions
so where what you see is going to depend
on where you look
we can make this implicit dependent
dependence explicit using the chain rule
of calculus
active inference it's inference about
action
so here's
the rate of change of action
through time
is the rate of change of a free energy
functional of
previously it was of observations and of
states through time
and now
o is o of a observations are a function
of action they're partially or
completely dependent on action
and that is being understood as a
derivative of change in action
o of a over a partial of a over a
is a forward model which makes explicit
the dependence of the observation upon
action and must be provided or learned
by the act by the algorithm
because that is
how do observations
which are a function of action change
as actions change
so that is like a layer that hadn't been
brought up so they're saying because you
do need to solve that ratio or that
derivative
you do need to like learn that or be
provided that
and it's a separate
thing to learn in addition to this
standard generative model for perception
so we talk action
as being like a dependency
of observations
which is also what connects active
inference to perceptual control theory
so that's how we introduce action into
the picture just from a first
pass
let's go one more um
level in and then any thoughts you have
would be great so
if we were talking about just
the inference case
prediction error minimization would be
like the picture that we're seeing is
exactly the one that we're predicting or
vice versa so what does that look like
for action
the prediction error simply becomes the
difference between the current
observation and the target or set point
already bringing in this kind of
homeostasis allostasis perspective
however this raises the question of
where the set points comes from
where do the targets come from and how
are they computed
whence priors
a generic answer to the question is that
set points can be inherited from
evolutionary or ontogenetic which are
developmental imperatives
or supplied by other neural circuits
involved in goal-directed behavior and
planning
for present purposes we can simply take
them as exogenously given variables so
what isn't addressed in this review is
this big question of
priors and learning on preferences like
how do you know what to prefer
how do you know how much to change how
you prefer
how tight should your preferences be
those are like really really important
areas but they're just like opening the
door but not going to go into it
in 4.5.1 it's also straightforward to
model the potential costs of action
in biological organisms there's
different costs of action
and so how can that be modeled
mathematically
well they say by
explicitly including action within the
generative model as follows
and so now they've added in this extra
term with a cost of action
so it just shows how like once action
has been introduced as a dependency
of the observation function
then there can be like
other things that can be calculated
related to action
any thoughts on action or like in your
readings where has action been
integrated well or not
with
predictive coding
um
well i think that
from the
from my perspective
predictive coding
wasn't really about action before this
text so it was
new to me because i always relate to
action to predictive processing and
active inference not really predictive
coding so it was new
and
from all of these that we've been
through uh i found fascinating how
the complexity grows and how many
different applications predictive coding
can be found on especially in machine
learning and
you know all of
this
uh mathematical
um
heaviness
uh brings many many different solutions
to problems that we face for a long time
so
fascinating
nice yeah agreed it's really interesting
so just one more take on active
inference which we explored in 26 as
well
like predictive coding pid control
optimizes the system towards the set
point and is ideal for simple regulatory
systems like thermostats
action aft
so we're taking that same notion of a as
being like
something that influences observations
so that's how we introduce action into
the model is we make observations depend
on action
action is determined by three terms
a proportional term which minimizes the
distance between the current location
and the set point
p
an integral term which minimizes the
integral of this error over time i
and a derivative term which minimizes
the derivative of the error d
the combination of the three terms
produces a robust and simple control
system which can be applied with some
tuning to control almost any simple
regulatory process
and higher coordinates of motion could
do even better but as we explored in 26
like often the pid is sufficient
and so that's a very common engineering
method and so it connects
the bayesian mechanics of action and
perception and cognition of active
inference on generalized coordinates to
pid control in the engineering setting
and then they provide a bunch of other
formalisms
in appendix b
they give some detail on this idea of
natural gradients
which i think we could go into in the
dot one and in the dot two
so we won't talk about it here but
appendix b is about precision as natural
gradients
and appendix c
are providing some challenges for the
neural implementation of back
propagation by predictive coding so also
we're not gonna explore it here but
those are both really interesting short
and very topical appendices
in section five it's uh
of quite good length and we're not gonna
cover actually any of it today because
it's been a great and long enough dot
zero but in the dot one and the dot two
and beyond we hope to unpack the
discussion and the future
directions
so
we have a lot of room and space for
questions
and i think we both or all walk out of
this with more questions than answers
but what would be your closing thoughts
maria
um
i'm not sure what to think now i have to
digest all the information we have here
today
but
i have this
this wish to continue uh with the
understanding of formalisms i want to
um you know understand better what you
said here and
i'm really excited about the biological
part of
predictive coding implementation and
predictive processing
so as it is not
really developed in this
paper i think that the author said
that uh it's not really explored
actually
i
i have this
this idea of you know looking to it to
see what's what's been do been doing
uh in in the past years
awesome
yeah i think it'll be some fun upcoming
discussions thanks so much for all the
help and for this dot zero and to brock
as well so
see you around thanks a lot
see you
bye
you